Okay, welcome back.
And let me start this week again by a bit
of programming, actually working with one
of the examples from last week and playing
around with it a bit to recall some concepts.
So, we had this example, I
think it was example four.
And well, on the slides, there was this picture “Parabolic
throwing” (Physics famous example: projectile motion).
And then there was this animation, which basically
translates that mathematical formula to Haskell.
And what I already briefly discussed
last week on this example was scoping.
So, how names introduced for variables as
function arguments, for example, how they
can be used, or where they can
be used, what the scope is.
So, for example, this t here, which is an argument
to the 'scene' function, is used here and here.
Yes, it doesn't have to be passed somehow
forward as a function argument to these local
definitions because they are subject
or part of the scene definition.
That's why they are not global definitions,
global functions that would only be living
on a top level here, then they
couldn't have got access to t.
So, this was one thing that this scope from
this t extends over the whole right-hand side
of the function definition.
So, of course, also inside these local definitions
for x and y. On the other hand, these x and
y can be used here because this “where … blah,
blah, blah” is a local definition relative
to this right-hand side expression here.
Okay, so that's why these
x and y can be used here.
And these x and y really mean what comes
after this “where”. And I also discussed that
you could also have used the “let”, where
you would first say, “let x = y = etc…”
in”, and then you would have this
expression that would be equivalent.
Okay, then I want to play around with this
a bit.
And there are some things, of course, that
we can do, that have already been discussed
also in the exercise videos, for example,
that it's nice to introduce some names for
parts of the definition.
So, for example, in this case, you could say,
well, this apparently is the ball that is
moved around.
So, maybe we want to actually make this explicit.
So, introduce a function with exactly this
call.
And of course, this is equivalent
to the previous piece of code.
But we can also more explicitly, for example,
say what the type of this function is, and that
might at least serve as additional documentation.
And maybe it's also helpful if you
want to refactor this code a bit.
Okay, what could we decide to refactor here?
Well, for example, and that's something I
didn't do last week, we might want to not
have just one ball with one fixed velocity,
so these 3 and 6 somehow, of course,
encode the velocity, whereas this
9.81 encodes the gravity constant.
Okay, so let's say we want to be parametric
over this, then we could, for example, say,
well, maybe these three
and six are not important.
Maybe the important thing here is the
angle at which the ball starts moving.
And that actually depends on the ratio
between these two constants here.
So, maybe, let's say we introduce some velocity,
and then instead of three and six, you have
v and 2 × v.
Okay.
And of course, for v set to 3, that's
exactly the same picture as before, the same
animation, nothing will have changed.
But now, of course, it could also take some other
constants here and get a faster moving ball,
but starting at the same angle.
Okay.
And then once we have this, you could go further and
say, well, let’s parameterize this. Let’s actually
draw several balls.
Yes.
How could you do this?
So, currently, the ball is used as a function
to express ultimately dependence on time via
these x and y coordinates, which
depend on the time parameter t.
So, that's why we have this animation
where the ball is making a movement.
If you want to have several balls, then you
can do the kind of trick that we did last
week already with a list
comprehension. In the exercise,
we have done our list comprehension with just
numbers, but we have already seen last week
that we can use a list comprehension on pictures.
So, we could say something like:
let me actually throw many balls.
Yes.
And somehow they are built or
parameterized by the velocity.
So, let's say I want to do
something like five balls.
So, for v chosen from two to six, instead
of just a fixed three, then maybe I have to
get rid of this v here.
And maybe it will work.
No, it doesn't.
Okay, why doesn't it work?
Well, let's see what CodeWorld is telling
us.
It has to do with scope, of course.
Yes, okay.
Hmm, I'm not sure whether this
message tells us exactly this,
but ultimately, that is what is happening
here.
Namely, we used the v here.
But where could it come from?
One could think, well, maybe it comes from
here.
But that's not true, because the scope
of this v is this list comprehension.
Right?
So, first of all, we don't use the v here
that somehow suspicious that in the body of
this list comprehension, we
don't use the v parameter.
And also, there's no way how this v parameter
could somehow reach these local definitions
here, because the scope of such a
generator is the list comprehension.
Okay, so what can we do in order
to get this v down to this place?
Well, we must turn x and y into functions.
They are not anymore just values, they are
functions because they depend on v, which
is very natural, right? For different velocities,
we will have different x and y coordinates.
So, these are functions.
So, we could introduce parameters here, turning
these into functions, and then these arrows
down here disappear.
Okay, that's nice, and it is nice. And it is even nicer,
or possible at least, to also provide type signatures.
For such local definitions, we can say, well,
x and y have now been turned into functions
from Double to Double.
Yes, it’s exactly what's happening here,
we get the Double, which comes from here,
then we compute a new Double, which
is supposed to be the x coordinate.
But then we still haven't somehow made the
connection from this v down to the use sites.
What do we have to do?
Well, if x and y are now functions, then we
cannot simply say that we use x and y as values.
Yes, x is now a function: given the velocity,
it gives back a Double value which is to be
used as a coordinate.
So, we also need to pass this v here.
And if we do this, then one could
have expected that the types work out.
Why is that not the case?
Let me check.
Okay, well, that was another mistake.
Another thing that was missing.
Well, of course, I cannot
simply say, this list of balls…
this list of Pictures is
combined with this cliff.
So, if you actually remember the
example from last week (example 3),
where I did something like this, when I
used the list comprehension in a Picture.
I also have to say, well, actually, I want
to turn this list of Pictures into a Picture.
And that's what this “pictures” primitive does.
So, this was an issue that
was overlaying all the others,
but also this aspect of x not being a function
before, so, I didn't have a way to communicate
the v from here to there.
It was also a valid concern.
And now I fixed them all together.
Okay, so what will I get if I now run this?
Well, I should get five balls that start at the
same angle, but move at different velocities
because this parameter v for velocity impacts both
the x and y coordinates, and then if I actually
do this, I get something like this.
Okay, let's see it again.
Okay.
And well, of course, it is not somehow
tied to this extra function 'ball'.
Of course, I could have done the same
without this indirection to “ball”.
So, I could, for example, now inline
this again, so ball x y is actually:
translated x y circle.
So, I don't have to do this in an extra function.
It was just for illustration.
Of course, I could also
have written it like this.
I’ll move this again here.
And then this does exactly the same thing,
because I have just restructured my definitions.
But maybe I like the previous version better.
Let me see whether I can get back to this.
Yes.
I'm missing the “translated” call down here.
So, then that's the version I end up with.